Guide to the Slam Stewart Papers
Yale University Music Library
Slam Stewart Papers
1938-1988
1960-1988
MSS 59
Yale University Music Library
12.0
(19 boxes)
The Papers document the latter part of Slam Stewart's career, during his appointment at SUNY Binghamton. Stewart gave many concerts and lectures during this time – locally, nationally and internationally. He also played in many jazz festivals. The collection includes photographs, music, correspondence, and sound recordings from this time, and highlights the collegial nature of Stewart's career. Fellow musicians such as Peter Appleyard, Jack Martin (a.k.a., "Ludwig Sigmund von Christ"), Bucky Pizzarelli, Benny Goodman, Slim Gaillard, Major "Mule" Holley, Carrie Smith and Dick Hyman (among many others) appear in several series in the collection.
Stewart, Slam, 1987-
Scope and Contents
The Papers document the latter part of Slam Stewart's career, during his appointment at SUNY Binghamton. Stewart gave many concerts and lectures during this time – locally, nationally and internationally. He also played in many jazz festivals. The collection includes photographs, music, correspondence, and sound recordings from this time, and highlights the collegial nature of Stewart's career. Fellow musicians such as Peter Appleyard, Jack Martin (a.k.a., "Ludwig Sigmund von Christ"), Bucky Pizzarelli, Benny Goodman, Slim Gaillard, Major "Mule" Holley, Carrie Smith and Dick Hyman (among many others) appear in several series in the collection.
The Music series contains jazz band and combo arrangements – many of which are jazz standards. The 200 sound recordings are mostly dubs of commercial recordings (some of which may be rare), but also contain some unique material. Photographs include portraits of Slam Stewart, as well as Stewart with friends and family. Programs, clippings and publicity document Stewart's appearances at festivals and various concert series in the U.S. and abroad.
The Playlists (set lists) indicate the order of songs played at live shows in which Slam Stewart played, and the tour schedules outline Stewart's performances in the later part of his life. Correspondence includes letters from colleagues, friends and fans. The collection also includes some contracts and awards.
Separated Materials
Music Library files indicate that photographs from this collection may have been moved into the Stanley Dance Papers (MSS 62).
Related Materials
Researchers may wish to consult the Stanley Dance Papers (MSS 62), the Benny Goodman Papers (MSS 53), and the Red Norvo Papers (MSS 48), all held by the Gilmore Music Library.
Biographical / Historical
Leroy Elliott "Slam" Stewart was one of the pre-eminent double-bass players in American jazz. Born in Englewood, New Jersey on 21 September 1914, Stewart originally studied the violin but soon switched over to the bass. During his years at the Boston Conservatory of Music, he developed his signature technique of bowing and humming a melody simultaneously at the interval of an octave. In 1935, he began a successful partnership with the guitarist Slim Gaillard – the duo called themselves "Slim and Slam." Their song, "Flat Foot Floogie," became very popular. In 1941, Stewart joined Art Tatum's trio, with which he appeared intermittently until Tatum's death in 1956. He also formed his own ensembles on 52nd or "Swing" Street, with the pianists Billy Taylor, Erroll Garner, and Johnny Guarnieri. Stewart appeared in several Hollywood films, including "Hellzapoppin" (1941) and "Stormy Weather" (1943). He also played with Benny Goodman's Sextet and Big Band, from 1945 to 1947. During the 1950s, Stewart performed with Roy Eldridge's Quartet and the pianist and singer Rose Murphy. Stewart also played with some of the leading Bop musicians, notably Dizzy Gillespie and Charlie Parker.
In 1971, SUNY Binghamton invited Stewart to join the music faculty. During this time, Stewart toured extensively, appearing with the Goodman Sextet, Bucky Pizzarelli, and the Newport Jazz Festival All-Stars, among others. Stewart also turned his attention to Baroque and Classical repertoires, assisted by the Lincoln and Lenox Quartets and the harpsichordists Christine Lindsay and Frances Cole. Stewart received many awards, as well as a Grammy nomination. In 1984, SUNY Binghamton awarded him an honorary doctorate. Stewart died in Binghamton on 10 December 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Leroy Elliot ("Slam") and Claire Stewart.
Arrangement
The Slam Stewart Papers contain 11 series: I. Music; II. Sound Recordings; III. Photographs; IV. Programs; V. Clippings, publicity, and posters; VI. Playlists; VII. Tour schedules; VIII. Writings and correspondence; IX. Contracts and financial materials; X. Awards; and XI. Miscellaneous.
Jazz musicians; Stewart, Slam, 1987-
- Music, circa 1960 - circa 1980
  Arrangement
  The Music is organized alphabetically by title, with the composer's name in parentheses. If an arranger's name is present on the document, his/her name likewise appears in parentheses.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains jazz band and combo arrangements. Some of the arrangements contain scores and/or parts - others have only a bass part. Most of the arrangements are jazz standards. Also included are a few compositions/arrangements by Slam Stewart.
  - Unpublished and manuscript scores
    - Acapulco (Jack Martin, arr.); Ah, Oui! (Hank Jones); Air from Suite in D Major (J.S. Bach); Alla Turca (Mozart); Anytime Anywhere (Kent McGarity); Ave Maria (Schubert) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bach Bourrees; Ballad; Ballad Section; Baroque 'n' Lute Blues; Les Bicyclettes de Belsize/You've Made Me So Very Happy; Blue Bossa (Kenny Dorham); Bluesette (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bourree No. 1 and 2 (Bach, Stewart, arr.); The Boss; Bowin' Bach (Bach, Stewart, arr.); Breaking Up is Hard to Do; Brown Ballad (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bucky's Waltz; Cadenza; Close Your Eyes; Come Sunday (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Concertino (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Corn Pone (Jack Martin, arr.); Cute; Del Sasser (Sam Jones); Nice Going Dick Tracy (Kent McGarity); Donna Lee (Charlie Parker) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - A Dragon is a Drag; Eleanor Rigby; Ellington Medley; The Lonely Dragon (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Emily (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Evil Ways (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Feelings (Jack Martin, arr.) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fifty Second Street Theme (Thelonious Monk) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Flat Foot Floogie (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Flat Foot Floogie (Jazz Band Arrangement by Al Hamme) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Flat Foot Floogie (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Flat Foot Floogie (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Flat Foot Floogie (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - For the Good Times; Fot's Alma Mater/Fot's Fight Song; Funtime All 'Round Town (Jack Martin, arr.); Gavotte (Bach, Stewart, arr.); Gavotte + Doubles (Rameau, Jack Martin, arr.); Greensleeves (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - The Happy Dragon; Hello Hello (I Hate Saying "Goodbye") (Kent McGarity); Hi, Mommy; How Can I Explain (What You Mean To Me) (Kent McGarity); I Can't Find the Words (Kent McGarity); I Got Rhythm (Gershwin) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - I Know That You Know/I Know; I'll Speak to You in a Song (Kent McGarity); I Wake up with You on My Mind (Kent McGarity); I Want to be with You (To-Nite) (Kent McGarity); Invention #14 (Bach, Stewart, arr.) (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Joy (Jerry Niewood [i.e. Gerry Niewood]); Just Say Hi (Kent McGarity) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Little Child (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Little Lamb (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Lover; Lurking Around (Jack Martin, arr.); Lute Prelude/Greensleeves (Bach) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Maid Marian and Sir Slamalot (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Masquerade (Bobby Francavillo, arr.) (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Medley (John Oddo, arr.); Minuet (Bach, Stewart, arr.); Minuet in G (Paderewski, Stewart, arr.); Mood Indigo (Jeff Friedman, arr.); Musette (Mozart, Stewart, arr.); My Ann Theresa (Major Holley) (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - My Lady Carey's Dompe (Jack Martin, arr.); My Romance; Never Let Me Go; Nightwind; Nobody's Gigue (Farnaby) (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Oh Me, Oh My, Oh Gosh; Pavana-The Earl of Salsbury (Byrd); Pavane (Faure); Pick Yourself Up; Pine Top Boogie (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Play Fiddle Play (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Praeludium (Jack Martin, arr.); Prelude (Jack Martin, arr.); Prelude (Cole, arr.); Prelude #1 (Bach); Prelude #2 (Bach); Prelude V (Bach); Prelude VI D minor (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Pretty Potty (Ludwig von Christ); Quartett No 29 (Haydn) (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Reve Symphonique Pour Slam (Jack Martin) (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Reve Symphonique-Ballad (Jack Martin, arr.); Round Midnight; Ruby My Dear; Sanctus From St. Cecilia Mass (Gounod); Sarabande (Bach, Stewart, arr.); Scratch My Bach (Stewart, arr.) (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - [Selections] Paris Bounce; Left Bank Swing; Shake It But Don't Break It; One Good Turn; Nervous Waltz; Passing Through; Dreamy; Something Happens; Solitare; When Paris Cries; Shenandoah; Shufflin' (Jack Martin, arr.) (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Slam to First Bass (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Slam to First Bass (Jack Martin, arr.) (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Slambitious (Robert Francavillo); Slam-Bow (Peter Appleyard); Slam/Mule; Smedley (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Sonata in C Major (Mozart, Jack Martin, arr.); Spain; Stella by Slamlight; Step Softly (Jack Martin, arr.); Stolen Moments (Oliver Nelson); La Suite Pour Slam (Robert Francavillo); Summer 42 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Surge; Symphony #3 (Mozart); Take a Chance (Kent McGarity); Le Tambourin (Rameau, Stewart, arr.); Tears (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Terezia; Tic-Toc Choc (Christine Lindsay, arr.); A Time for Love; Today is the Nicest Day (Kent McGarity); Today is what Tomorrow is Made of (Kent McGarity); Ton a Steps (Kent McGarity) (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Twilight World; [Untitled]; Ursala Igneous (Jack Martin, arr.); Variations on "Lison Dormait" (Al Hamme); Variations on a Nursery Tune (Mozart, Stewart, arr.); Variations on a Theme of Gluck (Stewart, arr.) (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Vivace Molto (Haydn, Stewart, arr.); Wabbit (Ludwig von Christ); A Waltz (Jack Martin, arr.); What is this Thing Called Love (Cole Porter); Yankee Doodle Variations (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - You Don't Know Me (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Published music
    - Nice! Nice! Nice! (Alain Bideaux); The Bass Tradition (Todd Coolman); The Man I Love (George Gershwin); Isn't Leroy Cool (Gregory Nathan) (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - The Flat Foot Floogee (Slam Stewart and Slim Gaillard); String Bass Styles (Slam Stewart) (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - The Reader's Digest Children's Songbook (Box 5, Folder 45)
- Sound recordings and video, 1938-1987; 180; 20; 2 (Box 18–20)
  The Slam Stewart Papers contain roughly 200 sound recordings – mostly cassette tapes, and a few reel-to-reel tapes. Artists who appear on these recordings include Erroll Garner, Slim Gaillard, Red Norvo, Bucky Pizzarelli, Benny Goodman, Ludek Hulan, Rose Murphy, Al Hamme, Major ("Mule") Holley, Carrie Smith, Dick Hyman and Louie Bellson. A handful of tapes are most certainly unique, for example, Slam and Bucky Pizzarelli chatting, and a rendition of "Potty", a tune that commemorates the bathroom in Stewart's house in Binghamton, upon whose walls his friends wrote their signatures. Other content includes interviews, radio broadcasts (in particular, memorials for Slam Stewart), and some live shows in which Stewart played. The vast majority of the tapes, however, are dubs of other (likely commercial) recordings. They appear to be mix tapes made for Stewart by his friends and colleagues. Among these, probably the most notable are dubs of commercial European discs from the 1940s, sent to Stewart by people he met while touring there. Note that many of these original recordings can be found in Historical Sound Recordings, including labels such as Black and Blue (France) and Savoy Records (U.S.). There are two videotapes in this series, which contain the following programs: Security Mutual Concert (Binghamton, NY) 1986; Artscene Interview with Slam Stewart 1983; Action News featuring Claire Stewart (Binghamton, NY) 1988; Tribute concert for Slam Stewart 1988; Benny Goodman Let's Dance [tribute concert] 1986; The Best of Everything - Frank Sinatra [Slam Stewart is mentioned in the beginning of the program].
  Conditions Governing Access
  The videotapes have been digitized. Please contact Special Collections staff for access.
- Photographs, circa 1930 - 1987
  Photographs are organized by subject and number of people: "Slam Stewart Alone," "Slam Stewart with one person," etc.). In the subseries "Slam Stewart Alone," black and white and color photographs are separated. When possible, the names of additional people are indicated.
  Photographs include portraits of Slam Stewart, as well as Stewart with friends and family. This series contains two photo albums.
  - Slam Stewart Alone
    - Early B&W Photos (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Color Photos (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Color Photos (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Color Publicity Photos (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - B&W Photos (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - B&W Photos (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - B&W Photos (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - B&W Photos (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - B&W Photos (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - B&W Publicity Photos (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Large B&W Photos (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Oversize B&W photos (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Slam Stewart with one other person
    - Ruby Braff; Dave Brubeck; Billy Butterfield; J.L. Carina (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Francis Cole (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Tal Farlow; Jim Ford; Slim Gaillard; Bobby Hackett; Hans Harzheim; Major Holley (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Christine Lindsay (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Bucky Pizzarelli; Marian McPartland; Willie Ruff; Zoot Sims (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Claire Stewart (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Teddy Wilson; [?] Boyd; Bobby Hackett; Tal Farlow; Unidentified (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Slam Stewart with two or more people
    - Billy Moore; Prince Carter; Charlie Christian; Red Norvo; Claire Stewart; Major Holley; Milt Hinton; Zoot Sims; Don Morgenstern; Kingman Brewster; Willie Ruff; Dizzie Gillespie; Louis Bellson; Len Skeat (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Major Holley; George Duvivier; Peter Appleyard; Claire Stewart; Janet Sprout; Eubie Blake; Francis Cole; Hank Edwards; Joe Hilla; Unidentified (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - Willie Ruff; Claire Stewart; Steven Clark; Frank Williams; Paul Quinichette; Beryl Backer; Georges Delerue; Bertrand Blier; Bob Rosengarden (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Jimmy Shirley; Jackie Williams; Johnny Guarnieri; Pat Flowers; Richard Wyands; Gray Sargent; Bucky Pizzarelli; Billy Butterfield; George Mosso; Peter Appleyard; Butch Miles; Sarasota Jazz Club (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Bands and ensembles
    - Benny Goodman Ensemble (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - Unidentified String Quartet (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Art Tatum Trio; Benny Goodman; North Sea Jazz Festival; Jazz Festival of Bordeaux (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - Unidentified Ensembles (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Other photographs
    - 1984 Doctorate Ceremony; Yale Ellington Festival (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - Funeral (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - Funeral (Box 9, Folder 92)
    - Claire Stewart (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Autographed Photos: Alain Bideaux; Bobby Hackett; Major Holley; Erroll Garner; Jackie Williams (Box 9, Folder 94)
    - Photo album: family, friends, wedding, 1968-1969 (Box 9)
    - Photo album: friends, events, performances, 1971-1987 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous and uinidentified (Box 9, Folder 95)
- Programs, 1969-1988
  This series contains programs in which Slam Stewart appeared, including festivals in the U.S. and abroad.
  - 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - 1971 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - March - April 1974 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - July - November 1974 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - 1975 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - 1976 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - 1977 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - 1980 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - 1983 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - 1984 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - 1985 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - 1986 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Undated (Box 7, Folder 62)
- Clippings, publicity and posters, circa 1960 - 1989
  This series is divided into three subseries: Clippings, Publicity, and Posters. Each subseries is organized chronologically.
  - Clippings
    Contains newspaper clippings about Slam Stewart from around the U.S., including the Philadelphia Daily News, Indianapolis Star, San Francisco Chronicle, New York Times, Chicago Sun Times, and various local papers in Binghamton, NY.
    - Clippings, Before 1966 (Box 10, Folder 96)
    - Clippings, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 97)
    - Clippings, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - Clippings, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Clippings, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - Clippings, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 101)
    - Clippings, January-July 1973 (Box 10, Folder 102)
    - Clippings, July-December 1973 (Box 10, Folder 103)
    - Clippings, January-June 1974 (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Clippings, July-December 1974 (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - Clippings, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - Clippings, January-June 1976 (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - Clippings, July-December 1976 (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - Clippings, January-June 1977 (Box 10, Folder 109)
    - Clippings, July-December 1977 (Box 10, Folder 110)
    - Clippings, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 111)
    - Clippings, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 112)
    - Clippings, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 113)
    - Clippings, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 114)
    - Clippings, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 115)
    - Clippings, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 116)
    - Clippings, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 117)
    - Clippings, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 118)
    - Clippings, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 119)
    - Clippings, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 120)
    - Clippings, 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 121)
    - Clippings, undated (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - Publicity
    This subseries includes press releases, newsletters, posters, flyers and arts calendars.
    - Publicity, 1960s (Box 11, Folder 123)
    - Publicity, 1970s (Box 11, Folder 124)
    - Publicity, 1980s (Box 11, Folder 125)
    - Publicity, undated (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - Posters (Box 17, Box 20, Folder 3, Folder 4)
    Subseries contains several concert posters - two are autographed.
- Playlists (Box 13, Folder 134, Folder 135, Folder 136, Folder 137, Folder 138)
  The playlists (set lists) indicate the order of songs played at live shows in which Slam Stewart played. The playlists are undated and do not indicate venue. A couple of the playlists include commentary about the songs themselves, and Stewart also wrote down exactly what he was to say between tunes. Also included is a playlist that outlines Stewart's presentation to school children about the origins and history of jazz.
- Tour schedules, 1971-1986 (Box 13, Folder 139, Folder 140, Folder 141, Folder 142, Folder 143)
- Writings and correspondence, 1960-1978
  This series contains correspondence, lectures, biographies and discographies. Correspondence includes letters from colleagues, friends and fans, including Beryl Booker, Marian McPartland, and Ronald Reagan.
  The series is divided into four subseries, including Correspondence, Lectures, Biographies and Discographies, and Writings by Others. The correspondence is organized chronologically, while each of the other subseries is organized by subject.
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence - 1960s (Box 11, Folder 127)
    - Correspondence - 1970s (Box 11, Folder 127a)
    - Correspondence - 1970s (Box 11, Folder 127b)
    - Correspondence - 1980s (Box 11, Folder 127c)
    - Correspondence - 1980s, no date (Box 11, Folder 127d)
  - Lectures (Box 12, Folder 128)
    Jazz History Lecture, SUNY Binghampton, 1971; "Swing Era" Talk; Motivational Speech
  - Biographies and discographies
    - Biographical Portrait by Monday Date Jazz Circle Zurich (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - "Sir Slamelot" by Jack Martin (Box 12, Folder 130)
      Details of Slam's life in Binghampton c. 1968 (stories)
    - Biographical Sketches (Box 12, Folder 131)
    - Interviews (Box 13, Folder 132)
    - Discographies (Box 13, Folder 133)
  - Writings by others (Box 13, Folder 133a)
- Contracts and financial materials, 1965-1986
  Series contains American Federation of Musicians contracts for various gigs. Financial materials include a work visa for the U.K., tax documents, and handwritten expense records.
  - Contracts (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - Financial materials (Box 13, Folder 145)
- Awards, 1971-1988 (Box 14, Box 15, Box 20, Folder 1)
  Contains honorary doctorates and awards from institutions such as the Sertoma Club, the American Legion, the National Academy of Recordings Arts and Sciences, and the Jazz Musicians' Foundation. Includes papers awards and wooden plaques.
- Miscellaneous
  - Artwork (Box 13, Folder 146, Box 20, Folder 2)
    Amateur drawings, comic strips and an informational brochure for oil portrait of Slam Stewart (portrait is housed in the Music Library). Also included are several prints signed "Pezuce Bates".
  - Catalogs and reports (Box 13, Folder 147)
    Various arts institutions' reports, record catalogs, and a calendar in which Stewart appears. Signed record jacket.
  - Passport and datebook (Box 13, Folder 148)
  - Music stands
    Two large, folding wooden music stands. Painted red and white with "Slam Stewart" on the front.